<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\transforms\module2html.xsl"?>

<?xml-model href="../transforms/schemas/CCModule.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<Module xmlns="https://niap-ccevs.org/cc/v1"
    xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    name="Host Agent"
    boilerplate="yes"
    target-products="Host Agent">

  <PPReference>
    <ReferenceTable>
      <PPVersion>1.0</PPVersion>
      <PPAuthor>National Information Assurance Partnership</PPAuthor>
      <PPPubDate>2019-01-20</PPPubDate>
      <Keywords>Host Agent, ESM</Keywords>
    </ReferenceTable>
  </PPReference>

  <RevisionHistory>
    <entry>
      <version>1.0</version>
      <date>2019-01-07</date>
      <subject>Draft - first version released</subject>
    </entry>
  </RevisionHistory>
  
  <chapter title="Introduction" id="int">
    <section title="Overview" id="ppoverview"> The scope of this PP-Module is to
      describe the security functionality of a Host Agent in terms of <abbr linkend="CC"/>
      and to define functional and assurance requirements for such products. This Module 
      is not complete in itself, but rather extends the Protection Profile for 
      Application Software <cite linkend="bibAppPP"/>. The combined requirements 
      in this Host Agent Module with the Application Software PP is meant to be paired with an evaluation using 
      an Enterprise Security Management (ESM) Protection Profile. The ESM PP covers the security 
      functionality needed on the server or cloud service, and the paired Host Agent Module
      covers the security functionality needed on the endpoint device (desktop, mobile device, 
      etc.). At this time only the ESM <cite linkend="bibEDRPP"/> PP is published and ready for use with
      this Host Agent Module. Future
      versions of this Module will include requirements for other classes of Enterprise Security 
      Management software.
    </section>
    <section title="Terms" id="glossary">
      <subsection title="Common Criteria Terms">
       <glossary>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Common Criteria">CC</abbr></term>
            <description>Common Criteria for Information Technology Security
              Evaluation.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Common Evaluation Methodology">CEM</abbr></term>
            <description>Common Evaluation Methodology for Information Technology Security
              Evaluation.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Protection Profile">PP</abbr></term>
            <description>An implementation-independent set of security requirements for a category
              of products.</description>
          </entry>
         <entry>
           <term><abbr title="Protection Profile Module">PP-Module</abbr></term>
           <description>An implementation-independent statement of security needs for a TOE type 
             complementary to one or more Base Protection Profiles.
           </description>
         </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Security Target">ST</abbr></term>
            <description>A set of implementation-dependent security requirements for a specific
              product.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Target of Evaluation">TOE</abbr></term>
            <description>
	      The product under evaluation. In this case, the Operating System as described in section 
	      <xref linkend="TOEboundary"/> and its
              supporting documentation.
	    </description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="TOE Security Functionality">TSF</abbr></term>
            <description>The security functionality of the product under evaluation.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="TOE Summary Specification">TSS</abbr></term>
            <description>A description of how a <abbr linkend="TOE"/> satisfies the SFRs in a <abbr
                linkend="ST"/>. </description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Security Functional Requirement">SFR</abbr></term>
            <description>A requirement for security enforcement by the <abbr linkend="TOE"/>.
            </description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Security Assurance Requirement">SAR</abbr></term>
            <description>A requirement to assure the security of the <abbr linkend="TOE"/>.
            </description>
          </entry>
       </glossary>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Technical Terms">
        <glossary>
         <entry>
           <term>Endpoint</term>
           <description>A computing device that runs a General Purpose Operating System 
             or a Mobile Device Operating System. Endpoints can 
             include desktops, servers, and mobile devices.
           </description>
         </entry>
         <entry>
           <term>Enrolled State</term>
           <description>The state in which an endpoint with a running Host Agent is managed by an ESM.
             Also, referred to as Onboarding.
           </description>
         </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>Enrollment</term>
            <description>The process of transitioning an endpoint from an unenrolled to an enrolled state.
            </description>
          </entry>
         <entry>
           <term><abbr title="Enterprise Security Management">ESM</abbr></term>
           <description>
             A enterprise security management application hosted on a server or cloud service that provides 
             support for security management, information flows, reporting, policy, and data analytics 
             in complex enterprise environments.
           </description>
         </entry>
         <entry>
           <term><abbr title="Endpoint Detection and Response">EDR</abbr> System</term>
           <description>A system that analyzes collected EDR Host Agent data for detecting, 
             investigating, and remediating unauthorized activities on endpoints. 
           </description>
         </entry>
         <entry>
           <term>Host Agent</term>
           <description>A logical piece of software that executes on endpoints to collect data about the endpoint,
             execute commands sent to the endpoint from an Enterprise Security Management (ESM) server
             or service. An example command sent to an endpoint could be to enforce a policy from an 
             ESM, or to collect some files, or to run an OS command.
           </description>
         </entry>
         <entry>
           <term><abbr title="Operating System">OS</abbr></term>
           <description> Software that manages physical and logical resources and provides services
             for applications.</description>
         </entry>
         <entry>
           <term>Unenrolled State</term>
           <description>The state in which an endpoint, with or without a Host Agent, is not managed by an ESM.
             Also, referred to as Offboarding.
           </description>
         </entry>
        </glossary>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Compliant Targets of Evaluation" id="TOEdescription">
      <subsection title="TOE Boundary" id="TOEboundary">
        The term Host Agent is the logical representation of all the software from the TOE
        vendor that represents the functionality of a Host Agent. The boundary for the Host Agent includes 
        all processes, all modules and libraries bundled with the Host Agent.  The Host 
        Agent can run as a daemon or service on the platform but is not required to. The Host Agent is
        not expected to have a local or remote Graphical User Interface (GUI) for administration but having 
        such an interface is not precluded by this Module. It is expected that Host Agents will be managed by
        their associated ESM Server or the underlying platform. 
        The TOE boundary includes the communications channel with other Host Agents, an ESM server, or a cloud 
        service. The platform operating system or execution environment
        upon which the Host Agent is executing is outside the scope of a Host Agent evaluation. The figures
        below show some sample Host Agents but are not inclusive of every possible Host Agent design. 
               
        <h:table>
          <h:tr>
            <h:td>
              <figure entity="images/Host_Agent.jpg" title="Sample Host Agent TOE" id="toe"/>
            </h:td>
            <h:td>
              <figure entity="images/Host_Agent_sample.jpg" title="Sample Host Agent TOE" id="toe"/>
            </h:td>
          </h:tr>
        </h:table>
        
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="TOE Platform" id="TOEplatform">
        The TOE platform consists of a General Purpose Operating System, a Mobile Device 
        Operating System, a Network Device Operating System, or an Execution Environment on top of which 
        the Host Agent software executes.
      </subsection>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">Requirements in this Protection Profile are designed to
      address the security problems in at least the following use cases. These use cases are intentionally
      very broad, as many specific use cases exist for an operating system. These use cases may also
      overlap with one another.  An operating system's functionality may even be effectively extended by
      privileged applications installed onto it.  However, these are out of scope of this PP. 
      <usecases>
        <usecase title="Communication" id="comms">
          <description>The Host Agent allows for communication interactively or
            non-interactively with other Enterprise Security Management (ESM) software over a communications channel.
            Example communications include but are not limited to; receiving policy, sending data and running tasks 
            or commands.
          </description>
        </usecase>
      </usecases>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter title="Conformance Claims" id="conf">
    <cclaims>
      <cclaim title="Conformance Statement">
        <description>
          <h:p>
            The Protection Profile for Application Software (<cite linkend="bibAppPP"/>)
            defines the baseline Security Functional Requirements (SFRs) and Security Assurance
            Requirements (SARs) for application software products. This <abbr linkend="PP-Module"/> serves to
            extend the AppSo PP baseline with additional SFRs and associated Evaluation Activities
            specific to a Host Agent.
            Evaluation Activities are the actions that the evaluator
            performs in order to determine an email client's compliance to the SFRs.
          </h:p>
          <h:p>
            This <abbr linkend="PP-Module"/> conforms to Common Criteria <cite linkend="bibCC"/> for Information
            Technology Security Evaluation, Version 3.1, Revision 5. It is CC Part 2 extended and CC
            Part 3 conformant. In order to be conformant to this <abbr linkend="PP-Module"/>, the <abbr
              linkend="ST"/> must include all components in this <abbr linkend="PP-Module"/> and the
            associated AppSo PP that are: <h:ul><h:li>unconditional (which are always required)</h:li>
              <h:li>selection-based (which are required when certain selections are chosen in the
                unconditional requirements)</h:li>
            </h:ul> and may include optional and/or objective components that are desirable but not
            required for conformance. 
          </h:p>
          <h:p>
            In accordance with CC Part 1, dependencies are not included when they are addressed by other SFRs.
            The evaluation activities provide adequate proof that any dependencies are also satisfied.
          </h:p>
        </description>
      </cclaim>
    </cclaims>
  </chapter>

  <chapter title="Security Problem Description" id="spd">The security problem is described in terms
    of the threats that the Host Agent is expected to address, assumptions about the
    operational environment, and any organizational security policies that the Host Agent
    is expected to enforce. 
    <section title="Threats" id="threats">
      <threats>
        <threat id="T.DATA_LOSS">
          <description>A Host Agent can be susceptible to data loss during periods when connectivity
            to the Enterprise Security Management (ESM) system is not present. 
          </description>
          <objective-refer ref="O.DATA_RECORDER">
            <rationale>The threat T.DATA_LOSS is countered by O.DATA_RECORDER as this
              provides for caching of data by a Host Agent during periods when not connected to the ESM 
              system.
            </rationale>
          </objective-refer>
        </threat>
        <threat id="T.TAMPER">
          <description>A Host Agent can be susceptible to tamper by unprivileged users who may try to uninstall
            or disrupt the Host Agents ability to function properly.
          </description>
          <objective-refer ref="O.ACCOUNTABILITY">
            <rationale>The threat T.TAMPER is countered by O.ACCOUNTABILITY and O.INTEGRITY which protect
              the Host Agent and report artifact up to the ESM system that could help to discover tampering.
            </rationale>
          </objective-refer>
        </threat>
      </threats>
    </section>
    <section id="Assumptions" title="Assumptions">
      <assumptions>
      </assumptions>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter title="Security Objectives" id="obj">
    <section title="Security Objectives for the TOE" id="SecurityObjectivesTOE">
      <SOs>
        <SO id="O.ACCOUNTABILITY">
          <description>Conformant Host Agents ensure that information exists that allows
            administrators to discover unintentional issues with the configuration and operation of
            the Host Agent.</description>
          <component-refer ref="FAU_GEN.1"/>
          <component-refer ref="FAU_STO.1"/>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is consistent with <base-name/>.
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SO>
        <SO id="O.DATA_RECORDER">
          <description>
            Conformant Host Agents ensure that collected information is cached or queued during periods
            when the trusted channel is not available. This will prevent data loss of Host Agent data.
          </description>
          <component-refer ref="FHA_CHA_EXT.1"/>
          <component-refer ref="FHA_COL_EXT.1"/>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is consistent with <base-name/>.
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SO>
        <SO id="O.INTEGRITY">
          <description>
            Conformant Host Agents will ensure the integrity of policy and/or commands sent to 
            the Host Agent and also leverage execution environment or platform-based mitigations
            to protect the Host Agent.
          </description>
          <component-refer ref="FMT_POL_EXT.1"/>
          <component-refer ref="FMT_UNR_EXT.1"/>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is consistent with <base-name/>.
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SO>
        <SO id="O.MANAGEMENT">
          <description>To facilitate management by the enterprise, conformant Host Agents
            provide consistent and supported interfaces for their
            security-relevant configuration and maintenance.
          </description>
          <component-refer ref="FMT_SMF.1(1)"/>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is consistent with <base-name/>.
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SO>
        <SO id="O.PROTECTED_COMMS">
          <description> To address both passive (eavesdropping) and active (packet modification)
            network attack threats, conformant Host Agents will use a trusted channel 
            for sending and receiving data.
          </description>
          <component-refer ref="FTP_DIT_EXT.1"/>
          <component-refer ref="FTP_DIT_EXT.2"/>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is consistent with <base-name/>.
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SO>
      </SOs>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Objectives for the Operational Environment"
      id="SecurityObjectivesTOEorEnvironment">The following security objectives for the operational
      environment assist the Host Agent in correctly providing its security functionality.
      These track with the assumptions about the environment. 
      <SOEs>
        <SOE id="OE.PLATFORM">
          <description>The Host Agent relies on being installed on a trusted
            platform.</description>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is inherited from the Base-PP. 
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SOE>
        <SOE id="OE.PROPER_USER">
          <description> The user of the Host Agent is not willfully negligent or hostile,
            and uses the software within compliance of the applied enterprise security policy.
           </description>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is inherited from the Base-PP. 
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SOE>
        <SOE id="OE.PROPER_ADMIN">
          <description> The administrator of the Host Agent is not careless, willfully
            negligent or hostile, and administers the Host Agent within compliance of the applied enterprise
            security policy. 
          </description>
          <consistency-rationale>
            This objective is inherited from the Base-PP. 
          </consistency-rationale>
        </SOE>
      </SOEs>
    </section>
    <section id="secconrat" title="Security Objectives Rationale">
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter title="Security Requirements" id="req">
    
    <base-pp 
      product="application"
      version="1.3"
      name="Application Software" short="AppSo" 
      url="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/Profile/Info.cfm?PPID=394&amp;id=394"
      xmlurl="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/commoncriteria/application/c51970161d3a47fe8a7c23552f372745a638ba7d/input/application.xml">
      <modified-sfrs/>
      <additional-sfrs>

     
      
      
      </additional-sfrs>
      
      <con-toe>
        If this PP-Module is used to extend the Application Software PP, the TOE type for the overall TOE is still an
        Software-based Application. The TOE boundary is simply extended to include the Host Agent functionality 
        that is built into the Application so that additional security functionality is claimed within the scope of the TOE.
      </con-toe>
    
      <con-sec-prob/>
      <con-obj/>
      <con-op-en>
        This PP-Module does not define any objectives for the TOE's operational environment. 
      </con-op-en>
   
    </base-pp>
    
	  <man-sfrs>
		   <subsection title="Security Audit (FAU)" id="fau">
       
        <f-component id="fau_gen.1" name="Audit Data Generation (Refined)">
          <consistency-rationale>
            This SFR defines the type of audit for a Host Agent that shall be logged.
            It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
          </consistency-rationale>
          <f-element id="fau_gen.1.1">
            <title> 
              The Host Agent shall generate an audit record of the following auditable events: 
              <h:ol type='a'>
                <h:li>Enrollment with an Enterprise Management System (Success/Failure);</h:li>
                <h:li>Change in enrollment state with an Enterprise Management System;</h:li>
                <h:li>
                  <selectables><selectable>Receiving</selectable><selectable>Generating</selectable>
                  </selectables> periodic heartbeat events
                </h:li>
                <h:li><assignable>other specifically defined auditable events</assignable></h:li>
              </h:ol>
              .
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              The required audit events must be generated by the Host Agent, but can leverage
              API's available from the platform if needed to generate the audit events.
            </note>
            <aactivity>
           <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
            
              <Guidance/>
              The evaluator shall check the administrative guide and ensure
              that it lists all of the auditable events.  The evaluator shall
              check to make sure that every audit event type selected in the ST
              is included.
              
              <Tests>
                <testlist>
                  <test>
                    The evaluator shall test the Host Agents ability to correctly generate
                    audit records by having the Host Agent generate audit records for the
                    events listed in the ST.
                  </test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
             
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="fau_gen.1.2">
            <title> The 
              <selectables>
                <selectable>Host Agent</selectable>
                <selectable>Host Agent Platform</selectable>
              </selectables> 
              shall record within each audit record at least the following information: 
              <h:ol type='a'>
                <h:li>date and time of the event,</h:li>
                <h:li>type of event,</h:li>
                <h:li>subject identity,</h:li>
                <h:li>(success or failure) of the event, if relevant,</h:li>
                <h:li><assignable>other audit relevant information</assignable></h:li>
              </h:ol>
              .
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              All audits must contain at least the information mentioned in FAU_GEN.1.2,
              but may contain more information. The term <h:i>subject</h:i> here is understood 
              to be the user that the process is acting on behalf of. The subject identity can
              be blank if not applicable for a given process.
            </note>
            <aactivity>
              
              <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
               
              <Guidance/>
              The evaluator shall check the administrative guide and ensure
              that it provides a format
              for audit records. Each audit record format type must be covered,
              along with a brief description of each field. The evaluator shall
              ensure that the fields contains the information required.
              
              <Tests>
                <testlist>
                  <test>
                    The evaluator shall test the Host Agents ability to correctly generate
                    audit records by having the Host Agent generate audit records for the
                    events listed in the ST.
                  </test>
                  <test>
                    The evaluator shall
                    ensure the audit records generated during testing match the
                    format specified in the administrative guide, and that the fields
                    in each audit record provide the required information.
                  </test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
                
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
      
        <f-component id="fau_sto_ext.1" name="Audit Data Storage">
          <consistency-rationale>
            This SFR defines how audit data for a Host Agent shall be stored.
            It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
          </consistency-rationale>
          <f-element id="fau_sto_ext.1.1">
            <title> 
              The
              <selectables>
                <selectable>Host Agent</selectable>
                <selectable>Host Agent Platform</selectable>
              </selectables> 
              shall store audit events in the platform provided logging mechanism.
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              The term <h:i>audit events</h:i> here is understood to be only the set of events
              defined in <linkref linkend="FAU_GEN.1"/>. If the job of this Host Agent is to generate
              or collect events for an enterprise security management server it is not expected 
              that those events will be stored in the platform provided logging mechanism.
            </note>
            <aactivity>
              
             <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
              
              <Guidance/>
              The evaluator shall check the administrative guide and ensure
              that the list of auditable events are stored in the platform provided logging 
              mechanism.
              
              <Tests>
                <testlist>
                  <test>
                    The evaluator shall test the Host Agents ability to correctly generate
                    audit records by having the TOE generate audit records for the
                    events listed in the ST.  This should include all instance types
                    of an event specified.  
                    When verifying the test results, the evaluator shall ensure the
                    audit records generated during testing are stored in the platform provided logging
                    mechanism. 
                    <h:br/>
                    On Linux based platforms this would be in var/logs. On Windows based 
                    platforms this would be the Windows Event Log.
                  </test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
          
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
       
        </f-component>
            
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection title="Host Agent (FHA)" id="fha">
       
        <f-component id="fha_had_ext.1" name="Host Agent Declaration">
          <consistency-rationale>
            This SFR defines the type of software the Host Agent is intended to operate 
            and communicate with.
            It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
          </consistency-rationale>
          <f-element id="fha_had_ext.1.1">
            <title> 
              The Host Agent shall operate with the following ESM Software; 
              <selectables linebreak="yes">
                <selectable id="AGT_EDR">Endpoint Detection and Response (EDR)</selectable>
                <selectable id="AGT_SM">Systems Management</selectable>
                <selectable id="AGT_AUD">Audit Server</selectable>
              </selectables>
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              Select the appropriate management system that is intended to be paired with 
              this Host Agent. Currently, a NIAP PP only exists for EDR. By selecting EDR 
              the additional <linkref linkend="FHA_CHA_EXT.1"/> and <linkref linkend="FHA_COL_EXT.1"/>
              requirements shall be included in the ST. 
            </note>
            <aactivity>
              
              <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
              
              <Guidance/>   
              The evaluator shall check the administrative guide and ensure
              that the Host Agent product under evaluation matches with the type of
              ESM under evaluation.
              
              <Tests>
                <testlist>
                  <test>
                    The evaluator shall install the Host Agent and enroll it with the EDR 
                    management system. The evaluator shall verify that enrollment was successful and 
                    that Host Agent is communicating with the EDR.
                  </test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
  
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>    
          <f-element id="fha_had_ext.1.2">
            <title> 
              The Host Agent shall restrict network communications to; 
              <selectables linebreak="yes">
                <selectable id="AGT_MGMT">a management server</selectable>
                <selectable id="AGT_PEER">another Host Agent</selectable>
              </selectables>
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              By selecting another host agent 
              the additional <linkref linkend="FTP_DIT_EXT.2"/>
              requirements must be included in the ST for peer-to-peer communication. 
            </note>
            <aactivity>
              
              <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
              
              <Guidance>There are is no associated guidance for this requirement.</Guidance>
              
              <Tests>
                <testlist>
                  <test>
                    While the Host Agent is running, the evaluator shall sniff 
                    network traffic ignoring all non-application associated traffic 
                    and verify that any network communications witnessed are documented in the TSS.
                  </test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
              
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>    
          
        </f-component>

      </subsection>
      
      <subsection title="Security Management (FMT)" id="fmt">
        
        <f-component id="FMT_SMF.1(1)" name="Specification of Management Functions (Configuration of Host Agent)">
          <consistency-rationale>
            This SFR defines a specific set of management functions for an email client.
            It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
          </consistency-rationale>
          <f-element id="FMT_SMF.1.2(1)">
            <title>The <h:b>Host Agent</h:b> shall be capable of the
              following management functions:
              <h:br/>
              <management-function-set default="O">
                <manager id="a">Administrator</manager>
                <management-function>
                  <text>
                    Configure the frequency for sending host agent data to an ESM
                  </text>
                  <M ref="a"/>
                </management-function>
                <management-function>
                  <text>
                    Assign at least one label or tag to categorize individual endpoint systems
                  </text>
                  <M ref="a"/>
                </management-function>
              </management-function-set>
            </title>
            <note role="application"> This requirement captures all the configuration functionality
              the <abbr linkend="TSF"/> provides the administrator to configure the Host Agent. The configuration of
              these management functions can be achieved by either local configuration of the Host Agent or by 
              remote configuration using the ESM management software.
              The frequency for sending data to an ESM can be specified as a time value, but does not have
              to be. A value like Aggressive, Normal, Low Bandwidth is a measure of control of frequency and meets
              the requirement.
            </note>
            <aactivity>
              
              <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
 
              <Guidance/>   
              The evaluator shall verify that every management function 
              mandated by the PP-Module is described in the operational guidance and that the description 
              contains the information required to perform the management duties associated with the 
              management function.
              
              <Tests>
                <testlist>
                  <test>
                    The evaluator shall test the ability to configure the Host Agent and test each option selected 
                    from above. The evaluator is expected to test these functions in all the ways in which 
                    the <abbr title="Security Target" linkend="ST">ST</abbr> and guidance documentation state
                    the configuration can be managed.
                  </test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
             
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
        
        <f-component id="FMT_UNR_EXT.1" name="User Unenrollment Prevention">
          <consistency-rationale>
            This SFR defines protections to prevent users from tampering with the Host Agent.
            It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
          </consistency-rationale>
          <f-element id="FMT_UNR_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The 
              <selectables>
                <selectable>Host Agent</selectable>
                <selectable>Host Agent Platform</selectable>
              </selectables> 
              shall enforce a mechanism to prevent unprivileged users of the platform from
              unenrolling the Host Agent with the ESM system.
            </title>
            <note role="application">
              Unenrolling is the action of transitioning from the enrolled state to the
              unenrolled state. Preventing unprivileged users from unenrolling the Host Agent
              provides assurance that the enterprise can manage connected endpoints. 
            </note>
            <aactivity>
                         
              <TSS/>
              The evaluator shall ensure that the TSS describes the mechanism used to
              prevent users from unenrolling the Host Agent.
              
              <Guidance>There is no associated guidance for this requirement.</Guidance> 
              
              <Tests>
                <testlist>
                  <test>
                    The evaluator shall attempt to unenroll the Host Agent from the ESM system
                    as an unprivileged user and verify that the attempt fails, by trying to kill the process
                    or stop the Service or Daemon that is running the Host Agent.
                  </test>
                </testlist>
              </Tests>
              
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>        
        </f-component>
        
      </subsection>
    </man-sfrs>
    
    <opt-sfrs></opt-sfrs>
    
    <sel-sfrs>
     <subsection title="Host Agent (FHA)" id="fha">
      <f-component id="fha_cha_ext.1" name="Cache Host Agent Collected Data">
        <selection-depends req="fha_had_ext.1.1" ids="AGT_EDR"/>
        <consistency-rationale>
          This SFR defines how the Host Agent shall cache data locally.
          It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
        </consistency-rationale>
        <f-element id="fha_cha_ext.1.1">
          <title> 
            The <h:b>Host Agent</h:b> shall cache collected data for a minimum of 72 hours on 
            <selectables>
              <selectable>persistent  storage</selectable>
              <selectable>non-persistent  storage
              </selectable>
            </selectables>
            if the trusted channel is not available.
          </title>
          <note role="application">
            The term <h:i>collected data</h:i> here is understood to be any type of collected endpoint data by the Host Agent
            destine for an enterprise security management (ESM) server. To meet this requirement a Host Agent must be
            capable of locally caching or queuing data for a minimum of 72 hours (3 days) during periods of network
            dis-connectivity. In a future revision the selection of non-persistent storage will be removed.
          </note>
          <aactivity>
            
            <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
            <Guidance>There is no associated guidance for this requirement.</Guidance>
            
            <Tests>
              <testlist>
                <test>
                  The evaluator shall test the Host Agents ability to cache data by disconnecting the endpoint
                  from the network for a period of 72 hours to simulate a network connectivity failure. The evaluator shall
                  exercise behaviors on the endpoint during the 72 hour time frame to generate Host Agent data.
                  Example behaviors could be running programs, performing some authentications, installing/uninstalling 
                  software, or sample test cases provided by the vendor to generate Host Agent data.
                  The evaluator will then reconnect the endpoint to the network and verify on the ESM system 
                  that the missing data from the 72 hour time frame is available on the ESM management portal.
                </test>
              </testlist>
            </Tests>
            
          </aactivity>
        </f-element>
        
      </f-component>  
      
      <f-component id="fha_col_ext.1" name="Collected Audit" >
        <selection-depends req="fha_had_ext.1.1" ids="AGT_EDR"/>
        <consistency-rationale>
          This SFR defines the type of software the Host Agent is intended to operate with.
          It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
        </consistency-rationale>
        <f-element id="fha_col_ext.1.1">
          <title>The Host Agent shall collect the following minimum set of
            endpoint event data: <h:ol type="a">
              <h:li>Operating System (OS) version, architecture, and IP Address</h:li>
              <h:li>Privileged and unprivileged endpoint account login activity</h:li>
              <h:li>Process creation</h:li>
              <h:li>Libraries and modules loaded by processes</h:li>
              <h:li>Network connection activity, including destination IP</h:li>
              <h:li>Files created on persistent storage</h:li>
              <h:li><assignable>other host data</assignable></h:li>
            </h:ol>
          </title>
          <note role="application">The intent of this requirement is to specify the minimum
            set of endpoint data that the Host Agent for an ESM EDR system must be capable of 
            collecting. This requirement only applies to Host Agents used with the 
            <cite linkend="bibEDRPP"/> PP per
            the selection from <linkref linkend="FHA_HAD_EXT.1"/>.
          </note>
          <aactivity>
            
            <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
            <Guidance/> 
            The evaluator shall check the administrative guide and ensure
            that it lists all of the collectable types of endpoint event data.  
            The evaluator shall check to make sure that every endpoint event 
            type listed in the ST is included in the administrative guidance.
            <Tests/>
            
          </aactivity>
        </f-element>
      </f-component>
     </subsection>
      
     <subsection title="Trusted Path/Channels (FTP)" id="ftp">
      <f-component id="ftp_dit_ext.2" name="Protection of Data in Transit for Peer-to-Peer Host Agents">
        <selection-depends req="fha_had_ext.1.2" ids="AGT_PEER"/>
        <consistency-rationale>
          This SFR defines the communication channel for Host Agents communicating with other Host Agents.
          It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
        </consistency-rationale>
        <f-element id="ftp_dit_ext.2.1">
          <title>The Host Agent shall encrypt all transmitted data with TLS 
            between itself and another Host Agent.
          </title>
          <note role="application">
            This requirement is designed to protection the communications with other Host Agents 
            in a peer-to-peer scenario where Host Agents are sending/receiving data from each other.
            If "encrypts all transmitted data with TLS" is selected the appropriate TLSC and TLSS requirements
            must be included in the ST.
          </note>  
          <aactivity>
            
            <TSS>There are no TSS activities for this requirement.</TSS>
            <Guidance>There is no associated guidance for this requirement.</Guidance> 
            
            <Tests>
              <testlist>
                <test>
                  The evaluator shall exercise the Host Agent (attempting to cause transmission of data)
                  while capturing packets from the Host Agent. The evaluator shall verify from the packet
                  capture that the traffic is 
                  encrypted with <h:abbr title="Transport Layer Security">TLS</h:abbr> or 
                  in accordance with the selections in the <abbr title="Security Target" linkend="ST">ST
                  </abbr>.
                </test>
              </testlist>
            </Tests>
            
          </aactivity>
        </f-element>
      </f-component>
     </subsection>
      
    </sel-sfrs>
    
    <obj-sfrs>
     <subsection title="Security Management (FMT)" id="fmt">
      <f-component id="FMT_POL_EXT.1" name="Trusted Policy Update">
        <consistency-rationale>
          This SFR defines protections for the integrity of commands sent to the Host Agent.
          It does not impact the AppSoftware PP functionality.
        </consistency-rationale>
        <f-element id="FMT_POL_EXT.1.1">
          <title>The 
            <selectables>
              <selectable>Host Agent</selectable>
              <selectable>Host Agent Platform</selectable>
            </selectables> 
            shall only accept policies or commands that are digitally signed
          </title>
          <note role="application">
            The intent of this requirement is to cryptographically tie any policy updates or
            commends sent to the Host Agent as being from the Enterprise. This is not to 
            protect the policies in transit as they are already protected by FTP_DIT_EXT.1.1
            and/or FTP_PTP_EXT.1.1. The digital signature used to sign policies or commands
            must be selected in FCS_COP.1.1(3). The use of this requirement makes FCS_COP.1.1(3)
            from the base Application Software PP a mandatory requirement.
          </note>
          <aactivity>
            
            <TSS/>
            The evaluator shall ensure that the TSS describes how the candidate 
            policies or commands are sent to the Host Agent; the
            processing associated with verifying the digital signature of the policies or
            commands; and the actions that take place for successful (signature was
            verified) and unsuccessful (signature could not be verified) cases. The
            software components that are performing the processing must also be
            identified in the TSS and verified by the evaluators (this could be the Host Agent
            or the underlying platform).
            
            <Guidance>There is no associated guidance for this requirement.</Guidance>
            
            <Tests>
              <testlist>
                <test>
                  The evaluator shall perform or wait for a policy update or commands 
                  from an ESM Server to be sent to a Host Agent. The evaluator shall verify the
                  policy or command is signed and is provided to the Host Agent. The evaluator shall
                  verify the Host Agent accepts the digitally signed policy.
                  <h:br/>
                  <h:br/>
                  The execution of this test may require some configuration or a test version of either
                  the Host Agent of the ESM system in order to view the incoming policy or command
                  and verify that the content is digitally signed.
                </test>
              </testlist>
            </Tests>
  
           
          </aactivity>
        </f-element>        
      </f-component>
     </subsection>
    </obj-sfrs>
    
  </chapter>

  <bibliography>
    <cc-entry/>
    <entry id="bibAppPP">
      <tag>AppPP</tag>
      <description>
        <h:a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/pp/PP_APP_v1.1/">Protection Profile for Application Software</h:a>
      </description>
    </entry>
    <entry id="bibEDRPP">
      <tag>EDR</tag>
      <description>
        <h:a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/pp/">Protection Profile for Endpoint Detection and Response</h:a>
      </description>
    </entry>
    <entry id="bibCC">
      <tag>CC</tag>
      <description>Common Criteria for Information Technology Security Evaluation - <h:ul>
        <h:li><h:a href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/files/ccfiles/CCPART1V3.1R5.pdf">Part
          1: Introduction and General Model</h:a>, CCMB-2012-09-001, Version 3.1 Revision 5,
          September 2012.</h:li>
        <h:li><h:a href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/files/ccfiles/CCPART2V3.1R5.pdf">Part
          2: Security Functional Components</h:a>, CCMB-2012-09-002, Version 3.1 Revision 5,
          September 2012.</h:li>
        <h:li><h:a href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/files/ccfiles/CCPART3V3.1R5.pdf">Part
          3: Security Assurance Components</h:a>, CCMB-2012-09-003, Version 3.1 Revision 5,
          September 2012.</h:li>
      </h:ul></description>
    </entry>
  </bibliography>
  
  <acronyms>
      <entry>
        <term>AES</term>
        <description>Advanced Encryption Standard</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ANSI</term>
        <description>American National Standards Institute</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>API</term>
        <description>Application Programming Interface</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ASLR</term>
        <description>Address Space Layout Randomization</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CESG</term>
        <description>Communications-Electronics Security Group</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CMC</term>
        <description>Certificate Management over CMS</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CMS</term>
        <description>Cryptographic Message Syntax</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CN</term>
        <description>Common Names</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CRL</term>
        <description>Certificate Revocation List</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CSA</term>
        <description>Computer Security Act</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DEP</term>
        <description>Data Execution Prevention</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DES</term>
        <description>Data Encryption Standard</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DHE</term>
        <description>Diffie-Hellman Ephemeral</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DNS</term>
        <description>Domain Name System</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DRBG</term>
        <description>Deterministic Random Bit Generator</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DSS</term>
        <description>Digital Signature Standard</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DT</term>
        <description>Date/Time Vector</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DTLS</term>
        <description>Datagram Transport Layer Security</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>EAP</term>
        <description>Extensible Authentication Protocol</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ECDHE</term>
        <description>Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman Ephemeral</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ECDSA</term>
        <description>Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>FIPS</term>
        <description>Federal Information Processing Standards</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DSS</term>
        <description>Digital Signature Standard</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>HMAC</term>
        <description>Hash-based Message Authentication Code</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>HTTP</term>
        <description>Hypertext Transfer Protocol</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>HTTPS</term>
        <description>Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DSS</term>
        <description>Digital Signature Standard</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>IETF</term>
        <description>Internet Engineering Task Force</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>IP</term>
        <description>Internet Protocol</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ISO</term>
        <description>International Organization for Standardization</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>IT</term>
        <description>Information Technology</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ITSEF</term>
        <description>Information Technology Security Evaluation Facility</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>NIAP</term>
        <description>National Information Assurance Partnership</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>NIST</term>
        <description>National Institute of Standards and Technology</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>OCSP</term>
        <description>Online Certificate Status Protocol</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>OID</term>
        <description>Object Identifier</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>OMB</term>
        <description>Office of Management and Budget</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>OS</term>
        <description>Operating System</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>PII</term>
        <description>Personally Identifiable Information</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>PKI</term>
        <description>Public Key Infrastructure</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>PP</term>
        <description>Protection Profile</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>RBG</term>
        <description>Random Bit Generator</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>RFC</term>
        <description>Request for Comment</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>RNG</term>
        <description>Random Number Generator</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>RNGVS</term>
        <description>Random Number Generator Validation System</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>SAN</term>
        <description>Subject Alternative Name</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>SAR</term>
        <description>Security Assurance Requirement</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>SFR</term>
        <description>Security Functional Requirement</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>SHA</term>
        <description>Secure Hash Algorithm</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>S/MIME</term>
        <description>Secure/Multi-purpose Internet Mail Extensions</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>SIP</term>
        <description>Session Initiation Protocol</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>SWID</term>
        <description>Software Identification</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>TLS</term>
        <description>Transport Layer Security</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>URI</term>
        <description>Uniform Resource Identifier</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>URL</term>
        <description>Uniform Resource Locator</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>USB</term>
        <description>Universal Serial Bus</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>XCCDF</term>
        <description>eXtensible Configuration Checklist Description Format</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>XOR</term>
        <description>Exclusive Or</description>
      </entry>
    </acronyms>
  
</Module>
