<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/esr2html.xsl"?>

<ESR xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/esr" name="Operating System Fundamentals">
  
	<intro>
		<esrtitle>Host Agent</esrtitle>
		<maintainer>NIAP</maintainer>
		<identifier>42</identifier>
		<version>1.0</version>
		<status>draft</status>
		<issuedate>March 9, 2018</issuedate>
		<approver/>
		<supercedes/>
	</intro>

	<section title="Background and Purpose" id="purpose">
		This document describes a core set of security requirements for host agent software. These requirements cover basic security
		characteristics and behaviors for host agents that run on managed endpoints to perform actions on behalf of, or report telemetry
		or other data to a management server.
		<br/>
		The intent is that the remaining sections provide succinct statements that highlight the relevant aspects to be
		addressed by the Technical Community (TC) constructing the PP. Here, the authors provide a narrative that introduces
		the reader to the problem being solved, and presents key aspects that support or guide the TC, and may elaborate on
		subtleties not apparent in the “bulleted” high level statements.
	</section>
	<section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">
		The Host Agent is responsible for receiving commands from a management server and send host data back to a 
		management server.
		<ul>
			<li>Collect Host data for transition to a management server</li>
			<li>Recieve commands from a management server and take action on those commands</li>
			<li>Cache data during periods without network connectivity</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Resources to be protected" id="resourcesprotected">
    	  <ul>
	        <li>Sensitive data collected or produced by the host agent in memory or in storage.</li>
    		<li>Cryptographic key material used to perform secure communications with management servers.</li>
    		<li>Sensitive data in transit to or from management servers.</li>
	  </ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Attacker access" id="attackeraccess"> 
		<ul>
			<li>An attacker is assumed to attempt attacks from the following vantage points:
				<ul>
					<li>The network across which the application engages in communication, both actively
						and passively.</li>
					<li>The platform on which the application is installed, though as an unprivileged
						subject.</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>An attacker has an arbitrary amount of time to analyze the behavior of the application,
				its interaction with its host device or platform, and/or the data it transmits over the network.</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Essential Security Requirements" id="requirements">
        	This is where the authors present an initial set of English 
        	requirements that specify security functionality, rather than 
        	design and/or implementation characteristics. These requirements 
        	will provide the foundation for which the detailed set of 
        	requirements is derived. It is important that the requirements 
        	captured here make an attempt to fully address the categories 
        	(e.g., access control, identification and authentication, 
        	management capabilities, roles of administration, secure 
        	communications, and audit). That's not to say the requirements are 
        	fully specified or detailed enough to simply translate to Common 
        	Criteria security functional requirements. The goal is that there 
        	is enough information contained here, as well as the other sections
        	of this document, to provide the TC enough information to ensure 
        	they have an understanding of what is minimally required in breath.

			<!--
			This is where the authors explicitly state english requirements
			that this class of product must satisfy. 
	        -->
		<li>The Host Agent shall use established encryption techniques (hashing, signing, etc)</li>
		<li>The Host Agent shall ensure encryption of all data in transit to and from any host agents using TLS or HTTPS</li>
		<li>The Host Agent shall be capable of handling periods without network connectivity</li>
		<li>The Host Agent shall store Host Agent audit records in the platform-provided audit storage.</li>
		<li>The Host Agent shall audit basic startup/shutdown and enrollment state events</li>
	</section>

	<section title="Assumptions" id="assumptions">
		Simply put, this section presents the aspects of the product and its intended environment that
		can be assumed to hold true. This will provide additional scope on the resulting protection profile.
		<br/>
		The following assumptions are made for the Host Agent and its operational
		environment:
		<ul>
			<li>The Host Agent is connected to a network. For purposes of sending/receiving data host agent data. Other
				entities on the network are not inherently trustable. </li>
			<li>Administrators are not malicious in nature.</li>
			<li>Users are not malicious in nature, though they may inadvertently or intentionally engage in risky behavior.</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Objective Requirements" id="objective">
		<ul>
			<li>
			
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Optional Extensions" id="extensions"> 
		Additional security functionality that may
		be appropriate for some use cases, and can be expressed in extensions to this document,
		includes: 
		<ul>
			<li></li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Outside the TOE's Scope" id="outsidescope">

		The following list contains items that are explicitly out-of-scope for any evaluation
		against the product PP <ul>
			<li>The operating system on which the Host Agent executes</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
</ESR>
